Guide to the Ira Gruber academic papers, 1934-2022 UA 204
Woodson Research Center, Rice University, Houston, Texas
- Series XI: Addendum, 174639
  This Addendum includes roughly one hundred fifty letters written between 1934 and 1982 to Ira Gruber's mother (Mary Louise Dempsey Gruber, 1909-1983). Ira Gruber and his wife, Patricia Sanderford Gruber (1929- ) wrote two-thirds of these letters to his "Mom." Their children—Anna, Talarah, and Conrad Gruber—wrote most of the remainder, all except a few letters from his mother's brothers Roger, James, and Donald Dempsey to their sister, "Lou." Some of Ira's and his wife's letters are addressed to both his mother and his younger sister, "Mary Lou" (Mary Louise Gruber Pollack, 1949- ).. His mother left only three drafts of replies: one to her son and two to the head of her daughter's school.
  Ira's letters to his mother were written while he was a student at Duke University, an officer in the U. S. Navy, a post-doctoral fellow at the Institute of Early American History and Culture, and a member of the history departments at Duke, the College of William and Mary, Occidental College, and Rice University. Taken together, Ira's letters complement his Academic Career Papers at Rice—providing glimpses of his reading, the academic advice he gave to his sister and children, and, especially, the research and writing he did between 1965 and 1980 when he published his first book and more than a dozen articles and lectures.
  - Correspondence, 2013; 174640 (Box 20, Folder 1)
  - Daily planner, 2013; 174642 (Box 20, Folder 2)
  - Graduate essays and papers, 1958-1961; 174643 (Box 20, Folder 3)
  - Undergraduate essays and papers, 1953-1955; 174641 (Box 20, Folder 4)
  - Correspondence, 2012 (Box 21, Folder 1)
  - Harvard Guide to American History (1960) with annotations by Charles Szalkowski while working for Ira Gruber, 1962 (Box 21)
  - Correspondence, 2014 (Box 21, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence, 2015 (Box 21, Folder 3)
  - Daily at-a-glance, 2014, 2015, 2016 (Box 21)
  - Correspondence, 2016 (Box 22, Folder 1)
  - Society for Military History - Program Committee correspondence, 2011 (Box 22, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence and photographs, 1979-2017 (Box 22, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence and daily planner, 2018 (Box 22, Folder 4)
  - Correspondence, 2018 (Box 22, Folder 5)
  - Correspondence and daily planner, 2019 (Box 22, Folder 6)
  - Publications (newspapers, newsletters, books), 1993-2004 (Box 22, Folder 7)
  - Correspondence and Daily Planner, 2020 (Box 22, Folder 8)
  - Correspondence and Daily Planner, 2021 (Box 23, Folder 1)
  - Price, Reynolds. A Long and Happy Life., 1962 (Box 23, Folder 2)
  - Ira Gruber CV and list of Doctoral students, 2022 (Box 24, Folder 1)
  - Rice Alumni Travel StudyProgram: Colonial/Revolutionary Virginia, 1985 (Box 24, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence, Ira and Pat Gruber to Mary Louise Dempsey Gruber, 1934-1981 (Box 24, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence, 1934-1968 (Box 24, Folder 4)